<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to Mr. Lowth's letter to Dr. Stillingfleet in another letter to a friend.</title>
            <author>Grove, Robert, 1634-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42255</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G2147</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31522</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12042856</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12042856</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53010</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42255)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53010)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1011:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to Mr. Lowth's letter to Dr. Stillingfleet in another letter to a friend.</title>
                  <author>Grove, Robert, 1634-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 5-38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Randal Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXVII [1687]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Grove by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lowth, Simon, 1630?-1720. --  Letter to Dr. Stillingfleet.</term>
               <term>Stillingfleet, Edward, 1635-1699.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:53010:1"/>
            <p>Licenſed, April 1. 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53010:1"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO Mr. Lowth's LETTER TO Dr. Stillingfleet.</p>
            <p>In another Letter to a FRIEND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Randal Taylor,</hi> near <hi>Stationers</hi> Hall. MDCLXXXVII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:53010:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:53010:2"/>
            <head>An Anſwer, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEcauſe you had ſo often deſired it, I have at laſt forced my ſelf to turn over Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi>'s <hi>Letter to Dr.</hi> Stillingſleet. I found it a very tedious and uneaſie Task: You had been almoſt as kind, if you had chang'd your Pennance, and ordered me to walk to <hi>Highgate,</hi> with Peaſe in my Shooes. The Way you ſent me proved ſo rugged and uneven, that every ſtep I took, I fancyed I was treading upon Cinders, and Pibble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones. But I am reſolved to be revenged; I'le ſend you another Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that ſhall be as troubleſome to you, as that was to me. But I'le promiſe you for your Comfort, it ſhall be ſcarce half ſo long, and not above a quarter ſo Ill-natured. I cannot imagine, what ſhould move Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> to fall upon the Dean in ſuch a manner: If it were pure Zeal, 'tis great pity, it had not been tempered with more diſcreſion; if there were any thing of particular Pique in the Caſe, it was not managed with Artifice enough. The World will never ſwallow the Potion, when the Venom ſwims on the top of the Cup.</p>
            <p>The firſt known occaſion of Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi>'s ingaging of Dr. <hi>Stillingſleet,</hi> was the Pretence of the <hi>Irenicum:</hi> A Book ſet out by the Dean in his younger Years, in which were many paſſages, which his riper Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment could not approve. And this he had ſignified to the World in other Writings which came abroad, before the Publication of Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi>'s Papers. But here you muſt note, the grand Objection againſt the <hi>Irenicum,</hi> had been formerly made by <hi>T. G.</hi> and his Companions; they had found, as they pretended, that the <hi>Deſign</hi> of it was <hi>only to Ruine and deſtroy the Church of</hi> England. And that was a thing, which they, Good men! were not able to indure; and therefore out of pure kindneſs, no doubt, they diſcover the Plot, and warn us of the danger we had cauſe to apprehend, from this young brisk Presbyterian, that had diſguiſed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53010:3"/>
himſelf in <hi>Irenicum</hi> Armour. The Truth of it is, they had reaſon enough to be very deſirous to be delivered from a troubleſome Adverſary. They ſaw by experience they were not able to oppoſe his force; and, to ſecure themſelves, they found it neceſſary, if poſſible, to give him a Diverſion. And this ſeaſonable aſſiſtance, Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> very wiſely affords them, by fomenting the Jealouſies they had cunningly raiſed.</p>
            <p>In his Treatiſe concerning the <hi>Subject of Church-Power,</hi> beſides ſome inſinuations in the Book it ſelf to the ſame purpoſe, there is a Letter to Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet, &amp;c.</hi> Printed after that to the Reader, wherein he is imperiouſly Summoned, and little leſs than Commanded, <hi>to ſatisfy the Church of God, by a recantation as publick as his Error, Scandal, and Offence:</hi> And then he is gravely admoniſhed, <hi>to conſider, that he has not erred in the</hi> Leviora Evangelii, <hi>and that the Point is, whether God has a Church on Earth, with its peculiar appropriated Power, or not.</hi> This bold and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate demand of Satisfaction, ſeconded with ſo heavy a Charge, urged upon him with ſo much fierceneſs, after he had given ſufficient Evidence of the contrary, and done the Church very conſiderable Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, upon ſeveral occaſions; could not chooſe but incline the Dean to reject the Calumny, with ſome degree of juſt reſentment. Which he did in a ſhort <hi>Epiſtle to my Lord Biſhop of</hi> London; where you may ſee, that he was not wholly inſenſible of the abuſe, but yet, notwithſtanding the great Provocation he had received, he could not be tempted to any rude and undecent expreſſions: Though Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> has ſnatched up ſome of them in haſte, and by the help of a rare Art of Compoſure, which he has gotten, has mixed, and altered, and jumbled them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I know not how, till he has made a ſhift, at laſt, to make them look almoſt as oddly as ſome of his own. This you will find he has done about the beginning of this Letter, which he tells us is, <hi>In anſwer to the Deans Epiſtle Dedicatory.</hi> For it was the gentle rebuke, which had been given him in that <hi>Two-penny Letter,</hi> as he elegantly calls it, that put him out of all Patience, and ſet his Blood into ſuch a violent fermentation, that I cannot obſerve any great abatement of the Paroxyſme for eighty four Pages together. It ſeems to be little elſe but a continued ſit of Paſſion, and the Dean is all along treated with that groſs diſreſpect, that it muſt needs be a very pleaſing entertainment to the Gentlemen of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Perſwaſion, to ſee him, who had frequently baffled the ſubtilleſt Advocates they could find, not confuted, but abuſed, and affronted by an angry Man of our own Church. This is certain, they were the only Men, I ever heard of, that applauded the Letter when it came abroad. His other Friends who were not much diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53010:3"/>
with his firſt Book, were quite aſhamed when they ſaw This: they had not a word that they could offer in defence of it. The moſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Readers were not able to frame any Apology for ſo much rudeneſs.</p>
            <p>That you may not think I load it with prejudice without a Cauſe, I will make it evident in ſome Reflections upon a few paſſages of the Letter, and then conſider the buſineſs of the <hi>Irenicum,</hi> which gave the occaſion to the whole Debate.</p>
            <p>If you look into the Dean's Epiſtle, you may obſerve that he has expreſſed a due ſenſe of the injury done him, but never let fall a word any ways unbecoming a Perſon of Civil and Ingenuous Education. But Mr. <hi>Lowth,</hi> as I intimated before, has raked together ſome ſcattered expreſſions, and by a ſtrange Liberty of adding, altering, and miſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying, as he thought beſt for his purpoſe, would make the World believe, that the Dean had repreſented him in a woful ſcandalous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. After ſome general flouriſhes of <hi>Clamorous Objections, riotous</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Noiſes, choice Epithets,</hi> and the like, he goes on thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If you can reap any ſatisfaction from loading me with the general Titles of a Plagiary, ridiculous fool, malicious, unskillful maker of Controverſies, a barbarous and rude Diſputer with his Brethren, an accuſer of his Brethren, an implacable Man, uncharitable, unjuſt, Slanderer, proud, void of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and common diſcretion, the uſual Complements you are pleaſed to beſtow upon me, you may be happy in the injoyment of your humour, though it hath not an Irenical Complection: But I that deſign nothing but the purſuit of Truth and Honeſty, &amp;c.</hi> And a very good <hi>Deſign</hi> really it is; and I hope he will be careful to keep it always in his eye.</p>
            <p>But I muſt look a little, and inquire into the <hi>Titles</hi> of Honour, he ſays he is <hi>loaded with, Plagiary:</hi> I cannot find this <hi>Title</hi> in all the Dean's Epiſtle, nor any thing from whence it may be gathered, without migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily ſtraining of his words. It has been always accounted an ill Omen to ſtumble at the Threſhold: therefore I ſhould be glad to ſee this firſt <hi>Title</hi> well reconciled with the grand <hi>Deſign of Truth and Honeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ridiculous Fool.</hi> This is ſomething like indeed! If he had been entred in a Diſpute at <hi>Billingsgate,</hi> or been contending with the <hi>Noted Scold in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 39.</note> 
               <hi>the Neighbourhood,</hi> whom he mentions afterward, he might have expected ſuch a <hi>Complement</hi> as this; but it is ſcarce credible, that the Perſon, he had choſen for his Adverſary, ſhould ever be tempted, upon the higheſt provocation, to let fall ſuch unſeemly ſcurrilous Language. I have turned to the Epiſtle again, and can find no ſuch <hi>Title</hi> there, from the beginning to the end. 'Tis true, in one place there is mention made of a <hi>Ridiculous Calumny,</hi> as every body knows all <hi>Calumnies</hi> are; and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53010:4"/>
in another, a pretty diſtance off, there is ſomething ſpoken of <hi>Folly;</hi> of which a Wiſe Man may be ſometimes guilty, as I ſuppoſe, by this time, Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> is ſufficiently convinced. For he has taken his advantage of this Word, and craftily clapt on a Pair of <hi>Midas</hi> his ears, and ſo very dextrouſly turns <hi>Folly</hi> into <hi>Fool,</hi> by an extraordinary skill he has in that kind of <hi>Metamorphoſis;</hi> and then he lays hold upon <hi>Ridiculous,</hi> and by main force drags it along, a matter of a dozen lines, and couples it with the <hi>Fool</hi> he had provided for it before hand, and when he had thus pacht up the Monſter, out he brings it with a Trumpet before it, and ſhews it abroad for one of Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi>'s Productions; and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains hideouſly how he had been abuſed by him. As if it were no better nor worſe, but that he had e'en dreſſed him up in a yellow Coat, and put Bells in his Cap, and expoſed him to the People for a <hi>Raree Show.</hi> Very fine ſport truly! But Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> muſt not think to impoſe upon his Readers at ſuch a rate. No: However, the Dean might ſpeak of ſomething that was <hi>Ridiculous,</hi> and of one certain <hi>Folly;</hi> it is very plain, that the <hi>Ridiculous Fool</hi> is of his own Making.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Malicious:</hi> This is ſuch another trick as the laſt. There was ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing intimated about <hi>Malice</hi> in a particular Caſe, and he very Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly changes <hi>Malice</hi> into <hi>Malicious;</hi> a ſingle Act into a Habit, by a Figure that is very familiar with him. He can beſt tell what reaſon he had for it; and therefore, I ſhall not offer ſo much as to conjecture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nskilful maker of Controverſies:</hi> This is the ſirſt <hi>Title</hi> that has been truely repeated. And I pray what great harm is there in it? That he <hi>made a Controverſie,</hi> where there was need of none, the <hi>Dean</hi> has prov'd; and with what skill he has managed it, let the World judge. But yet I muſt confeſs, I think the Dean was ſomething to blame here, for charging him with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nskilfulneſs in making of Controverſies,</hi> when he had ſhewn himſelf a moſt accompliſhed Artiſt, in that My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery at leaſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Barbarous and Rude Diſputer with his Brethren:</hi> He is quickly come back to his beloved <hi>Legerdemain,</hi> and has moſt nimbly turned <hi>a Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Style, and Rude way of Diſputing,</hi> into <hi>a Barbarous and Rude Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> by the vertue of <hi>Hocus Pocus: Hooper Hoper.</hi> But I perceive the Gentleman is eaſily provoked. What would he have had the Dean have ſaid, I wonder? Why, he ſhould have ſlattered him a little, and told him that he had a very Polite and Elegant <hi>Style,</hi> and that he <hi>Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> very civilly with him, and that he was a Courtier every inch of him. In good time! Let it be ſo then. But I'le go on to the next.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An Accuſer of his Brethren:</hi> This indeed is one of the <hi>Titles</hi> that is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53010:4"/>
given him in the Epiſtle. But what then? That he had accuſed Dr. <hi>Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingfleet</hi> of a very great Crime, he will not deny, and then I do not ſee what it is that he can take amiſs, unleſs it be that he is ſo Charitable as to account him a <hi>Brother,</hi> after he had uſed him ſo much like an Enemy. But if he be not pleaſed with the Name, let him learn to have a care of the Thing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An implacable Man:</hi> This is ſo far true, that the Dean does ſpeak of <hi>Implacable Men.</hi> So that 'tis evident, he muſt mean more than One. Yet I verily believe he did intend a good ſhare in the <hi>Title</hi> for Mr. <hi>Lowth;</hi> but he will not be contented with that, but very fairly takes it all to himſelf; and it may be he might have more reaſon than eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body knows of, to ingroſs the whole. For the <hi>Irenicum,</hi> which was the ſole occaſion of the quarrel, was publiſhed I think about 61; and his firſt Letter, wherein he ſends the Challenge, and demands fatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, bears date in 83; and ſure he may well be ſuſpected for an <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable Man,</hi> that will not be pacified in above twenty years.</p>
            <p>And now we are come to the bottom of the Liſt; and thus it runs: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitable, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt, Slanderer, Proud, void of Prudence and common Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion.</hi> Theſe, he ſays, are the <hi>Complements,</hi> and the <hi>uſual Complements</hi> too, which the Dean is pleaſed to beſtow upon him, and yet I have looked very narrowly over the whole Epiſtle, once or twice, and I'le aſſure you, there is not ſo much as one of all theſe ugly Words to be found there, that I can ſee. Theſe are <hi>Titles</hi> that he has taken to himſelf without any authority; and ſo is <hi>Fool,</hi> and <hi>Nonſenſical Fellow,</hi> which he complains of in another place. All this is meer <hi>Chimaera,</hi> nothing but an Apparition in his own diſturbed Imagination. And yet <note place="margin">Pag. 4.</note> I ſhould be apt to think, that he has ſome way or other to make out a Right to every one of theſe: Otherwiſe, ſure he would be affraid of being queſtioned in the Court Martial, for aſſuming of <hi>Titles,</hi> which never belonged to Him, nor any of his Predeceſſors. Certainly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he muſt be able to juſtifie his Claim, if it ſhould ever come to a Hearing. It is very well known with what an Inſolent Rudeneſs he ſet upon the Dean; and he could not but be ſenſible, what manner of Reply he might have juſtly expected. But herein, he was happily diſappointed, by the Mildneſs and Civility of the ſhort Anſwer that was returned him. And yet the Natural Remorſe of the Injuſtice he had done, might make him dread the ſeverity he had deſerved. The guilty Mind ſees its puniſhment always before it. And this might oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion him to miſtake the Laſhes of his own Conſcience, for the ſtrokes of the Dean's Pen. Or however it were; Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> may make bold,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53010:5"/>
and give himſelf as many ill Words as he pleaſes; I know, no ſober man will be offended at him: But when he would make us believe that all the rudeneſſes he offers himſelf, were ſhewn him by the Dean, there, I fear, he was a little unmindful of his great <hi>Deſign of Truth and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly.</hi> A man would imagine that he had had ſome other aim in it; and that he had induſtriouſly laid together a great heap of bad Language, with which he is very well ſtored, and pretended it to be the Dean's; that the credulous Reader, that was unwilling to be at the pains of a ſearch, and could not conceive that any man could be guilty of Forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that might be ſo eaſily detected, might be the better inclined to excuſe the rough uſage he gives him, all through the following Letter.</p>
            <p>You have had a view of the Dean's <hi>Complements</hi> to him, pray take notice now, in what a courtly manner he treats the Dean. If all the <hi>Titles</hi> and <hi>Complements,</hi> he ſays the Dean <hi>beſtowed upon him,</hi> had every one of them been his indeed, I'le promiſe you, Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> does not come a whit behind him: He ſcorns to bate him an Ace: He gives him every jot as good as he brings. I think he has ſo paid him off with <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements,</hi> that I believe the Dean will have a care, how he meddles with ſuch a ſtout Courtier again in haſte. When the Grand <hi>Seignior</hi> ventures upon another Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> it may be, not before, I'le warrant you: No, no, he enough of that already. But it is worth your while to conſider a little, what a ſine vein of <hi>Complements</hi> Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> has. I ſhall but juſt give you a taſte; though there be ſuch plenty of Proviſion of that kind in this Letter, that it were eaſie to furniſh a whole Table with three full Courſes. But you muſt not think to make a Meal on ſuch rare Dainties as theſe: You may be glad of a bit or two to reliſh your Mouth.</p>
            <p>Well then, one of the firſt <hi>Complements</hi> I chanced to caſt my eye upon, is that, where he charges the Dean with making <hi>a Concluſion he</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 3.</note> 
               <hi>alone can be guilty of, whoſe common Perceptions are choaked with Choler. Common Perceptions choaked with Choler!</hi> 'Tis a very clean one, though ſomething a bold Metaphor; Borrowed, I ſuppoſe, from ſome of the Neighbouring Farmers, that had neglected to ſcour their Ditches. Very Well! But is this <hi>Choler</hi> ſuch a mighty dangerous thing indeed? Then let him have a ſpecial care of his own <hi>Common Perceptions;</hi> if he has any <hi>Perceptions</hi> that be <hi>Common.</hi> For if he ſhould happen to fall into ſuch a fit of Paſſion, as he has been ſometimes known to be in; and that famous Channel, or whatever it be, of Invention ſhould chance to be <hi>Choak'd</hi> up, it may prove a very great Annoyance; and ſo for ought I know, may come within the Commiſſion of <hi>Sewers;</hi> and he
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53010:5"/>
may be made to pay ſoundly for that unlucky overflowing of his Gall. I would adviſe him thereſore, as a friend, never to be undecently an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry any more. He may take it as he pleaſes; but he will find, one of theſe days, that it is very good ſober Counſell. And ſo let that <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement</hi> paſs.</p>
            <p>About a leaf further he has a very pretty one, upon one of the Dean's Books, I think it is that ſame <hi>Irenicum,</hi> he calls it a <hi>Farce of all manner of Quotations.</hi> Another Metaphorical expreſſion, I believe; and a very dainty one too it is. But what! does not Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> like <hi>Quotations.</hi> There are a good many, I'm ſure, in this very Letter, that might have been very well ſpared: But I thought he had brought them in by Head and Shoulders, out of a particular kindneſs he had for all <hi>Quotations,</hi> whether they were material, and pertinent, or not. Yes; he loves <hi>Quotations</hi> well enough; but 'tis <hi>ſuch a Farce.</hi> That it is a very ill-favoured word truly. I think I have heard it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but I don't thoroughly underſtand the meaning of it yet: only when I read it, I remember my ſtomach was a little affected; I was almoſt Sick upon it. And I would caution you, if you have a mind to look upon the Letter again, be ſure not to do it till after Breakfaſt, for fear you ſhould be provoked to ſomething that were not ſo decent; as <hi>Mark Anthony</hi> was once in the Senate-Houſe at <hi>Rome.</hi> But out of the reſpect I bear you, I will entertain you no longer with theſe ſilthy noyſome expreſſions.</p>
            <p>But there is one of another kind, which though it do not belong im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to Dr. <hi>Stillingſleet,</hi> yet I cannot omit it, becauſe of a certain peculiar air it has, which, in my mind, is very ſurprizing. It is full as civil, but not altogether ſo dirty, as thoſe you have had: when you hear it, it does not ſtrike your fancy preſently, and make you imagine you were talking with Farriers and Scavengers. He is beholding for it to another; but he has adopted it for his own, by making it publick. He tells you therefore that he <hi>Heard an Honourable Perſon obſerve upon him [Dr. Burnet] That, for Six pence, Barbara,</hi> the renowned <hi>Barbara, a noted Scold in the Neighbourhood, would anſwer his Book better than he hath</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 39.</note> 
               <hi>done.</hi> A notable Compariſon! 'Twas very ſacetiouſly done though, of the <hi>Honourable Perſon,</hi> to fit Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> ſo exactly, with ſuch a ſuitable Antagoniſt. I can't tell what a ſhrewd Diſputant this <hi>Barbara</hi> may be; nor how it might have fared with him, if ſhe had happened to have ingaged in the Controverſie. But I gueſs he would have main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained his ground in ſpight of her Teeth. For if the <hi>Honourable Perſon</hi> will but be pleaſed to read this Letter, he muſt needs confeſs, it is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53010:6"/>
never to be outdone by <hi>Barbara</hi> her ſelf. Any one that had but looked into it, would be apt to think, indeed, that he had lived near a <hi>Noted Scold;</hi> and that he had been very induſtrious in taking all opportunities of improving himſelf, by that agreeable Converſation. But yet really, when I conſider it better, I will not undertake to determine whether he might go to School to <hi>Barbara,</hi> or <hi>Barbara</hi> to him: which<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever of the two have the Glory of it, 'tis plain, he met with a very apt Scholar. But does Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> know what he has done? ſee how Indignation will tranſport a Man; and make him run upon dangers, which he would dread to come near, in a cool and ſober mood! what if ſome body ſhould go tell honeſt <hi>Barbara,</hi> how ſhe has been blazoned abroad, and branded in Print, for a <hi>Noted Scold!</hi> What a Peal might Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> have at his door, the next morning! If ſhe really deſerve the Character he has ſixt upon her, ſhe would rattle him up for it to ſome Tune., Sure no Wiſe Man would offer to provoke ſuch an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, if he were not conſcious of his own abilities, and readineſs to bear the Encounter. He cannot but know the ſtrength of his Arm, and the advantage he has of the Weapon: Or if <hi>Barbara</hi> ſhould chance to be too brisk for him, in the way of <hi>Extempore</hi> Dialogue; he has a ſure retreat certainly ſecured; he may write her a Letter; and then, poor Girle! ſhe muſt be fain to croſs the Cudgels immediately; for alas! though ſome of them may be able to manage their Tongues pretty nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; yet I muſt tell you, it is not one <hi>Scold</hi> in a thouſand, that can handle a Pen, as he has done. Then farewell <hi>Barbara,</hi> till we meet again.</p>
            <p>It is time now to look for another <hi>Complement,</hi> and there is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent one to be had, in one of his Complaints of the Dean; where he tells us, that <hi>Inſtead of an Anſwer to matter of Fact, and Argument, he has only Libelled him to a principal Biſhop of our Church, in a Two penny</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 54<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>Paper; to which is tackéd (and therein,</hi> ſays he, <hi>your further diſingenuity ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears) one of your four penny Sermons.</hi> So the Bill of expences runs: <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primis,</hi> the <hi>Paper, Two pence: Item,</hi> the <hi>Sermon, Fourpence.</hi> A very accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate way of Calculation, lately invented, by a Well-Wiſher to the Mathematicks, ſor the uſe and better information of the Worſhipful Company of Hawkers! A curious new way of Complementing Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metically! I wonder at my heart, how he ever came to ſtumble upon it ſo luckily. I have a great conce it, he had been reckoning with his Pariſhoners for Petty Tithes; or diſcourſing the Market-Women, about the price of Butter and Eggs: Or it may be, he had been war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at a Friendly Conference with his good <hi>Neighbour Barbara.</hi> Or where ever he had the hint, it ſmells ranck of the Plowman, or the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53010:6"/>
               <hi>Scold,</hi> or both. Things are come to a ſine paſs, when Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> ſhall be ſhewing his Wit, and ſpending his Country kind of Drollery upon any of Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi>'s <hi>Papers.</hi> But let him ſet what rate he pleaſes on the Deans Writings; it is very well known how the World Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues His.</p>
            <p>But we have a <hi>Complement</hi> behind ſtill, worth ten of theſe. It is not a <hi>Two-penny,</hi> nor a <hi>Four-penny</hi> matter neither; nor any thing leſs than <hi>filling</hi> whole <hi>Pockets.</hi> This is ſomething to the purpoſe at laſt. It is ſet off to the beſt advantage, in a Mungrel kind of Allegory: I ſhould quite ſpoil it, if I ſhould go to take it aſunder; therefore I will give it you as it lies in the Letter; <hi>As the Church is the Tree in the Pſalmiſt; ſo Epiſcopacy is one of the Bearing Boughs:</hi> Very well! what <note place="margin">Pag. 31.</note> then? <hi>In which you can be content to ſit and ſing:</hi> A Metaphor taken from a Bird, that pearches up upon ſome of the higheſt Branches, and there merrily chants out his wild Notes, for a while. But how long will this be? <hi>So long as you fill your Pockets,</hi> and then the Tune will quickly be changed. But hold a little; <hi>ſit and ſing,</hi> and <hi>fill Pockets too!</hi> How's that? Alas! What a ſad misfortune is this! I could wiſh heartily, for the ſake of the Allegory, that it had been the Faſhion for <hi>Birds</hi> to have <hi>Pockets</hi> in their Breeches. But let that be as it will; we muſt drive on the Metaphor as well as we can. <hi>But when the gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring time is over, it is to be cut down as that which cumbereth the Ground.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This whole <hi>Complement</hi> you ſee is an Allegory pieced up with very Hetrogeneous parts; but that is a thing may be eaſily pardoned. But the plain meaning of it is this; that the Dean will be for <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> as long as he can get any thing by it, at leaſt till his <hi>Pockets</hi> be <hi>full</hi> enough, and then he will be for <hi>cutting of it down,</hi> Root and Branch, it may be. This every one knows, is as much as to call him Covetous Knave, baſe Hypocrite, one that acts againſt his Conſcience to get Money; and what not? But to have ſpoken this broadly out, had been two rude and clowniſh for Mr. <hi>Lowth.</hi> For I ſuppoſe, by this time you are pretty well acquainted with his <hi>Style.</hi> His conceits may be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a little ſharp and rough, but his expreſſions are highly Civil and Obliging. And therefore here he has couched all theſe ſcurvy inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions very neatly, in a ſimilitude of a <hi>Tree,</hi> and a <hi>ſinging Bird</hi> with <hi>Pockets,</hi> and an <hi>Ax</hi> at his back, ready to <hi>hew down the Tree,</hi> when time ſhall ſerve. But all his glozing will do him no good; we can ſee his meaning through his ſmooth Language. Don't you remember the <hi>Titles,</hi> and <hi>Complements</hi> he gave himſelf, which he ſaid the Dean <hi>Beſtow'd</hi> upon him? <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitable, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt, Slanderer,</hi> &amp;c. I told you I
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53010:7"/>
thought he was able to make every word of it good; and if he have not offered fair for it here, I am much miſtaken.</p>
            <p>And beſides this, he talks of the Dean, as if he were ingaged in a <hi>Party,</hi> and that's a very ill thing too you know. But I marvel what <note place="margin">Pag. 1.</note> this <hi>P<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ty</hi> is: I believe they are a parcel of thoſe <hi>Canary Birds,</hi> that are for ſelling the <hi>Tree.</hi> No doubt Mr. <hi>Lowth,</hi> if he pleaſes, can tell you how many and who they be, what their Opinions and Practices are, nay, what coloured Ribbons they wear in their Hats, to diſtinguiſh themſelves from another <hi>Party,</hi> that he knows of. But I would wiſh him to have a care, how he goes to making of <hi>Parties</hi> any more, before he has told Noſes, and be well aſſured of the ground he ſtands upon, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he may find it a very raſh, and unadviſed undertaking.</p>
            <p>Well: Now you ſhall have but one <hi>Complement</hi> more; (for I imagine you begin to have enough of it, as well as I) and that is in the ſecond of the three general Heads, he has divided his Letter into; there, ſays he, <hi>I ſhall make it appear, that the account you give of your Irenicum is not fair nor true.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The whole deſign and Plot being meerly againſt the Re-eſtabliſhment of the Church of England.</hi> But when he comes to the proof of this heavy charge, his heart miſgives him, and he qualifies <hi>Meerly,</hi> into <hi>Moſtly, if not altogether.</hi> However <hi>the account of the Irenicum is not fair nor true.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 29.</note> It ſhould ſeem then there has been ſome very foul and falſe play in the caſe. If this had been ſpoken ſo bluntly to ſome warm Hectoring Blade, it would certainly have made an uproar; and there might have been a Ducl upon it. 'Tis well for him he has to do with peaceable Men. But how does he know, that the <hi>Deſign</hi> was <hi>Meerly, Moſtly, if not altogether againſt the Re-eſtabliſhment of the Church of England.</hi> He that affirms ſo boldly, had need be very well aſſured. This is not a thing to be made out by a few ſlight airy Conjectures only; eſpecially when the Dean had ſolemnly declared he had another quite contrary <hi>Deſign:</hi> O! by vertue of a rare piercing Judgement, with the help of a very charitable Conſtruction, he has been inabled to tell the Dean's mind, a great deal better then he can himſelf. This is a wonderful extraordinary knack of underſtanding Mens <hi>Deſigns.</hi> But let the Dean's <hi>Deſign</hi> be what it will, He <hi>Deſigns nothing but the purſuit of Truth and Honeſty:</hi> And for all he will not believe the Dean, yet I hope you will be ſo Civil, as to take this upon his bare word. For if it ſhould be <note place="margin">Pag. 2.</note> queſtioned, it would be a task too difficult for Him to prove it. Though for my part I think he might. <hi>Meerly,</hi> or <hi>Moſtly, if not altogether Deſign nothing but the purſuit of Truth and Honeſty;</hi> For he <hi>purſues</hi> them ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53010:7"/>
as if he intended to make them run the Countrey. Pray look, and try how much of either you can diſcover in all this long <hi>Letter to Dr. Stillingfleet.</hi> Alas! Poor <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Honeſty!</hi> whither will you go? But I ſhall leave him a while, to conſider with himſelf, whether this were really his only deſign or not</p>
            <p>You may ſee, by theſe few paſſages, in what manner he <hi>Complements</hi> the Dean; If it were not too tedious, I could ſhew you as particularly, how Civil he is to his Books. Some he calls <hi>Such Stuff,</hi> charging them with <hi>Contradictions,</hi> and many imperfections at the Beſt. He is ſo <note place="margin">Pag. 74.</note> diſpleaſed with the <hi>Vindication of Arch-Biſhop Laud, that he does much queſtion, whether it might not have diſcompoſed the Calm, that moſt exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 73.</note> 
               <hi>Prelate died in, upon the Scaffold at Tower-Hill, if he could then have been aware that he ſhould have had ſuch a Vindicator.</hi> A wiſe remark! and he deſerves a great many thanks of ſome body for it. But no queſtion it would have quieted all again, and reſtored the former ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene temper, if his Grace had likewiſe foreſeen, how ſeverely his <hi>Vindicator</hi> was like to be chaſtiſed by ſuch a Man as Mr <hi>Lowth.</hi> But let that be as it will: I am ſure it would pleaſe you ſtrangely, to ſee him ſeated in his Chair, with his Cenſorial Rod in his hand, paſſing ſentence very Critically upon the Dean's Writings; and you would not think it, it becomes him mighty prettily. Let me give you but one Inſtance of his Judgment; it is concerning <hi>The unreaſonableneſs of ſeparation;</hi> of which, ſays he; <hi>I do not deny but that your performance is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 78.</note> 
               <hi>Competently well done;</hi> Indeed! <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon your Principles:</hi> Very good! and <hi>ſo far as it reacheth.</hi> 'Twas well enough offered then, it ſeems, but it falls ſhort of the main point. Moſt men were of another mind; but this is Mr. <hi>Lowth's</hi> Opinion; and he is a Man of a more than ordinary <hi>Reach.</hi> But he goes on and tells us what he approves, and what not: <hi>You have,</hi> ſays he, <hi>abundantly ſet forth the Reaſonableneſs of our Book of Common-Prayer,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and urged Obedience thereunto from the deſtructive conſequences, that muſt incvitably follow,</hi> &amp;c. This is <hi>Competently well done, ſo far.</hi> Now you ſhall hear his Exception. <hi>But all is ſtill left as matter of Diſpute, &amp;c. And he that ſees not with your Eyes (by your own princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples) hath no Obligation for Obedience, and Conformity to any one Rubrick, Law or Injunction therein contained.</hi> This is ſtrange, that <hi>the Reaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of a thing ſhould be <hi>Abundantly ſhewn,</hi> and the <hi>Deſtructive conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that muſt unavoidably follow</hi> the contrary perſwaſion, be made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; and yet that <hi>All</hi> ſhould he <hi>leſt ſtill as matter of Diſpute,</hi> and that <hi>no man had any obligation to Obediencce;</hi> at leaſt, <hi>if he did not ſee with the</hi> Dean's <hi>Eyes.</hi> I had always thought that every man had been bound to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53010:8"/>
yield to <hi>Reaſon;</hi> and that in matters of Diſcipline and poſitive Laws, we had been ſtrictly obliged to <hi>Obey</hi> the commands of a Legal Authority, which was here ſuppoſed, eſpecially when our non-ſubmiſſion is atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with <hi>deſtructive Conſequences.</hi> For theſe are a ſort of Practical Abſurdities, and ſlat Contradictions to the very Eſſence and Being of all Society. And as he is a ſtubborn and irreclaimable Caviller, that will not be convinced by what is <hi>Reaſonable;</hi> ſo that is a deſperate and untractable Member of any Corporation, whether Eccleſiaſtical or Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, that is not affraid of ſuch pernicious <hi>Conſequences,</hi> as tend to the Ruine and Subverſion of it. And it being frankly confeſſed, that the Dean has carried his Point both theſe ways; I cannot ſee what could be wanting to compleat the Argument, and give him the credit of an intire Victory. But unleſs a Man ſays whatever Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> imagines he ſhould, he will hardly acknowledge that he comes fully home to the purpoſe. He will be clapping in his diminiſhing Gradations: <hi>Competently well, upon your Principles; and ſo far as it reacheth.</hi> And now, what ſhould be the meaning of theſe mortifying expreſſions? I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not gueſs, unleſs it be that, if he had taken the Cauſe in hand, he would have done it <hi>Incomparably well,</hi> upon I cannot tell what <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples;</hi> and been ſure to have ſearched the whole matter to the very Bottom. 'Tis likely enough: And yet the Fanaticks are not ſenſible of the great danger they eſcaped, upon His declining to ingage in the Diſpute. But after all, I believe you think the buſineſs was as effectually done upon the whole account, as if Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> himſelf had undertaken it; whatever he is pleaſed to conceit to the contrary. For there is no ſort of Opponents the Dean ever had, but would have been glad to have ſhifted their Adverſary, and eſteemed it a great happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs if Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> had withdrawn, though Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> had preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtept forward, and thruſt himſelf boldly into his Place. There's none of them all, but would have thought it a lucky change for them; and if he does not know it yet, they can inform him where the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference lyes.</p>
            <p>You ſee he cannot forbear picking of quarrels with thoſe very Books, wherein the Dean had very ſucceſsfully endeavoured to defend our Church, againſt her open Enemies of all ſorts; and which had been received with general approbation, and highly applauded, if not admired, by very great numbers of his equals, at leaſt, for Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Learning. How he uſes to <hi>Complement</hi> the Dean himſelf, you have had ſome intimations; and beſides ſeveral others, I could eaſily gather up, there is a freſh tryal of his skill in that way, in the leaf
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53010:8"/>
I looked upon laſt. Where he tells him of his <hi>Having Mountebank'd, and Quack'd for full five and twenty years,</hi> &amp;c. And that <hi>The Colledge of Phyſicians, he is ſure, would not think themſelves beholden to ſuch an Empi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick.</hi> Is not this finely Civil, and curiouſly carried on under a very quaint Alluſion? You may perceive again, what a notable Faculty he has at perſecuting a Metaphor. But this is not the worſt: He of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten takes occaſion to intermix ſuch foul inſinuations, that if they were true, as they are not, they would render the Dean as Odious, as ſo much treachery and diſſimulation, as he would imply him to be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of, might moſt juſtly make him. And ſome of theſe are ſo utterly impertinent to the main buſineſs, that nothing but a very great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Good-will could carry a man ſo far out of his way, meerly to do his Friend a Kindneſs. But indeed he generally uſes the Dean with that diſreſpect and contempt, that it is not eaſie to conceive what the Cauſe of it ſhould be. 'Tis plain that he was the Aggreſſor, and upon no provocation, that ever I could hear of. I wiſh there be not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Envy and Emulation in it. He ſometimes talks of <hi>Stalls and accidental Dignities;</hi> and in this Letter he complains, that he <hi>finds a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 61.</note> 
               <hi>general Prejudice againſt him, becauſe he has not a Stall in a Cathedral.</hi> Really that's a very hard Caſe: For though he may not have a <hi>Stall,</hi> yet I dare ſay the fault can be none of his. But if this be all that troubles him, I hope after a while, to ſee him in ſomething a better Humour. For when once his great Deſerts come to be known; and it is noiſed abroad that there is a man found, that is able to incounter with Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> and make nothing of him too; his meer worth will quickly prefer him. So much Merit cannot be always overlooked.</p>
            <p>But though he may chance to be ſweeten'd in time, yet for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, there appears ſuch a ſowre temper all through this tedious Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that it is ſcarce to be matched with ſuch another piece of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſeneſs and Incivility. Sure, when he was writing, he did not mind the <hi>Stalls and accidental Dignities.</hi> A ſudden fit of impatience, may <note place="margin">Subject of Church Power. Pref. to Reader.</note> make a Man forget the <hi>Regard</hi> he once thought himſelf obliged to <hi>Pay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now after all this, and a great deal more, which I will not trouble you with, it is very pleaſant to obſerve how the Gentleman concludes: <hi>And thus (Sir)</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I beg only this favour of you, that if you think fit to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 84.</note> 
               <hi>return an Anſwer, you will do it in a Scholar-like way;</hi> i. e. <hi>by Argument,</hi> &amp;c. He means, 'tis like, according to the Copy which he has ſet him: But I fear the Dean will never be able to write after that. No, it is no ſuch eaſie matter. But he proceeds, and tells him very gravely:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53010:9"/>
               <hi>It is really below your quality in the Church, to act</hi> Andrew Marvel. Yes, the Advice is very good, and no doubt but it will be followed; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, ſince it comes from ſuch a hearty Friend. But how came this into his mind? What ſhould make <hi>Andrew Marvel</hi> run ſo in his Head? Why, in plain terms, he had uſed the Dean ſo very unhandſomly, that he could not be ignorant in what manner he might expect to be treated himſelf. The Guilt of his own unſufferable Rudeneſs, made him as fearful of being Jerked, as ever any School-Boy was, that had been playing the Truant. And this makes him fall into a very unu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Vein of Courtſhip: He talks of <hi>Begging of Favours,</hi> and being <hi>Anſwered in a Scholar-like way.</hi> Don't you wonder at the ſuddain al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of his <hi>Style?</hi> Alas! This is only to prevent being handled as he deſerves: Nothing but a kind of <hi>Quaeſo Praeceptor:</hi> A little Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling if poſſible, to eſcape Correction. Well! Let him be forgiven then, for this one time.</p>
            <p>But why ſhould not Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> like the <hi>Acting</hi> of Merry <hi>Andrew?</hi> He is for rare feats of Activity himſelf, ſometimes; and will ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be nibling at a Jeſt. And it may be he took his pretty Tale of <hi>Barbara</hi> to be One; and the <hi>Two-penny Paper tacked to the Fourpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sermon;</hi> and ſome others. But certainly he thought he had paid it off with his Greekiſh Quible, of <hi>Irenicum</hi> and <hi>Erynnicum.</hi> He would <note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g. 40.</note> be no enemy to a little Jeſting, if he could hope the advantage could ever lye upon his ſide. No: He is ever now and then offering at a flight of Wit, and fain would be upon the Wing, and flutters, and flutters, and as ſoon as ever he has, with much ado, raiſed himſelf a little above the dull Earth, down he tumbles again preſently; like a poor callow Bird that muſt be crawling out of the Neſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it can fly. And now ſince, beſides the general roughneſs and diſreſpect of the whole Letter, he has made ſo many vain attempts to play the <hi>Andrew,</hi> 'tis ſtrange, he ſhould think of being <hi>anſwered in a Scholar-like way,</hi> as he pretends to deſire. I cannot tell how he may take what I have written you already; it may be, he may call it <hi>Trifling</hi> and <hi>Buffoonery,</hi> and I know not what. But it is a very great miſtake. For ſuppoſe I had derided him never ſo much; yet he muſt know, that the expoſing of ill-manners is a very ſerious thing; and all the civilized World is concerned, not to ſuffer any noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Rudeneſs to paſs, without fixing ſome publick mark of ſhame and ſcorne upon it. <hi>Dr. Stillingfleet</hi> was a perſon of that known worth and Learning, and had done the Church ſo many eminent Services, that when he was aſſaulted in ſuch an angry and boiſtrous
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53010:9"/>
manner by Mr. <hi>Lowth,</hi> it had been a thing very pardonable, if he had been ſufficiently laught at for his Pains: The puniſhment had been too ſlight for the affront. But I have not taken the Liberty that might have been juſtly uſed. Inſtead of that, I have only choſen a few, out of very many unſeemly expreſſions, and indeavoured to ſet them in a true Light; that you might ſee the man in his proper colours. But there are ſome things ſo very foul, that they make a bare Narrative look like a Satyr: and ſome will complain that they are Ridiculed, if they be but fairly repreſented. It may be you have ſeen certain faces of ſuch an odd Compoſure, that if they chance to be drawn like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, you can hardly caſt your eye upon the Picture without a ſmile: But the fault is in the Original features, and not in the Painter, who is always bound to work by the Life. Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> may poſſibly think that I have put a great many ill-favoured Lines in this little Piece, and that I have not done him Right: But if he will but take his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the Looking-Glaſs, he will quickly be convinc'd, that all is but an exact Copy of his own Countenance. I have done no more but only touched a little upon a few, and but a very few, of a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of unhandſome expreſſions, and very uncharitable inſinuations: and if there be any thing in what I have ſaid, that may ſeem unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to him, he muſt conſider that it is nothing elſe but the reflection of his own rude and uncivil language; you may gueſs at the reſt, by the ſample I have given you. For beſides the general Air of the whole, there is ſcarce a Leaf that does not afford peculiar inſtances of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs and diſreſpect to the Dean. It were an endleſs and unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table labour to ſearch for them all; and if you are not weary yet with raking in ſuch a heap; I am.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore paſs on to the buſineſs of the <hi>Irenicum,</hi> which gave the occaſion to the whole Debate. And here I ſhall take notice, of the Writing of it, and how it was received when it came abroad: What we may reaſonably ſuppoſe to have been the <hi>Deſign</hi> of it? And whether the Dean hath not ſince given ſufficient <hi>Satisfaction</hi> for any material <hi>Errors</hi> and <hi>Miſtakes</hi> that might be in it.</p>
            <p>As to the Writing of the <hi>Irenicum,</hi> it was occaſioned thus. About the time of the happy Reſtauration of his late Majeſty, and the Royal Family, before the Church of <hi>England</hi> was re-eſtabliſhed by any new Act of Uniformity, all mens minds were full of expectation what might be the iſſue of ſo great a Revolution, and what influence it was like to have upon the Eccleſiaſtical State of the Nation. They that were for Epiſcopacy and the Legal Eſtabliſhment did not doubt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53010:10"/>
but that all things would return to the point from whence they had been violently removed, and that they would ſettle at laſt upon the old foundation. On the other ſide, they which Diſſented, and retained ſtill a very great fondneſs for their own Schemes of Diſcipline, and Government. were not without hopes that ſomething might be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in favour of Them. Theſe refuſed Communion with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſtood off with too great numbers of the People, who had not yet done waiting for ſome effect of thoſe many pretences of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with which they had been ſo long deluded. Upon the proſpect of ſo fatal a Diviſion, as the ſeparation of ſo great a Multitude was like to occaſion, the Dean at that time but a very young Man, boldly ventures upon the Reconciling part. It muſt be confeſſed, and he has acknowledged it himſelf, that according to the fate of moſt Reconcilers, he was too liberal in his Conceſſions. He had ſhewed that the Epiſcopal Government might not only be allowed of, but that it had the example of the Primitive times to recommend it; but then he thinks it mutable, and that it might be altered to ſome other form, if the Exigency, or convenience of the Church ſhould ſo require. This, as far as I am able to gather, is a true account of the writing of the <hi>Irenicum;</hi> the more particular Deſign of it will appear after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
            <p>Let us now ſee how it was received when it came abroad, and what the Diſſenters, what the Biſhops and regular Clergy, and what Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> thought of it; for his Sentiments about it ſeem to be very peculiar, and therefore he muſt make one member of the Diviſion by himſelf.</p>
            <p>Thoſe of the Diſſenters that were obſtinately reſolved upon their new Models, and ſo ſtrangely enamour'd with their own Fancies, that they could not hearken to any propoſals of accommodation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected this with the ſame contempt, that they had done all other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments that had been offered for their Conviction. But ſome of the more moderate that gave themſelves the liberty of conſidering calmly, were <hi>gained over</hi> to a ſubmiſſion to <hi>our Church. It did not want ſucceſs in that way, both here, and in a Neighbour Nation;</hi> as the Dean has told us. And we have no reaſon to queſtion the Truth of what he ſays. For when he had proved Epiſcopacy to be a warrantable Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment at teſt, and given it ſome advantages above other forms; it muſt be a more than ordinary degree of obſtinacy that could make men refuſe to be obedient to it, when they were once perſwaded of this; as probably very many were upon reading the <hi>Irenicum.</hi> But Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:53010:10"/>
eſteems this but a ſmall piece of Service, and reflects upon ſome that had <hi>received Epiſcopal Ordination,</hi> with how much Charity I cannot tell; and then he talks of <hi>keeping of Beniſices, and further acceſſion of Church</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Dignities.</hi> For whatever the matter is, theſe <hi>Dignities</hi> are ever and anon running in his Head. But at laſt he concludes this matter with his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted elegancy and reſpect: <hi>Sure I am, all the kindneſs you have done hereby to the Church of England, and her Biſhops, may be put in their Eyes, and they ſee never the worſe for it.</hi> O! the ingenuity of ſomeMen! Don't you remember the old Hob nail Proverb? Did you ever hear it ſo prettily applyed? But for all this I do not underſtand, but that it might be ſome <hi>kindneſs to the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and her Biſhops,</hi> to have the popular Odium removed, which the blind-Zeal, and importunate Clamours of ſome intereſted Men had fixed upon her, in the late Confuſions, It was ſomething ſure to make it appear that Epiſcopacy, that had been ſo violently decryed, as Tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and Antichriſtian, was not repugnant to the word of God, nor the Practice of the firſt and pureſt Ages of the Church. This might ſerve to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay thoſe Heats, and abate the Hatred that had been moſt unreaſonably raiſed againſt it; and make Men yield a quiet ſubmiſſion unto it. And they that were advanced ſo far, were fairly diſpoſed to proceed on, and from being perſwaded that Epiſcopal Government was allowable, might come to ſee it Neceſſary, as that which was undoubtedly of Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Inſtitution. Which was the Caſe of the Dean himſelf, and very probably of many Others. It is a good ſtep towards the receiving of the Truth, to have the Prejudices againſt it taken away. This at leaſt might be thought enough to bring back the generality of the People, that had been frighten'd from our Communion, in the times of Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion. It ſeems ſufficient for them to be ſatisfied of the Lawfulneſs of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy, without perplexing their Minds about the Divine Right of it; ſince Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> has acknowledged, that they cannot be competent <hi>Judges of ſuch Diſputes.</hi> Nay, I fear ſome that had been admitted into <note place="margin">Pag. 8.</note> holy Orders, were not throughly qualified to determine that Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, which depended ſo much upon ſome skill in Eccleſiaſtical Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and an inſight into the State of the Ancient Church. And many of theſe for ought he can tell, might be induced by what the Dean had written, to ſubmit to the Power, which they could not yet fully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate. And I believe there are very few real Friends, to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who do not think that it were ſome <hi>Kindneſs to Her,</hi> to bring thoſe over to a Conformity to her Diſcipline and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, who had otherwiſe remained profeſſed Diſſenters, and divided themſelves into ſeparate Aſſemblies. This certainly had been <hi>Competent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well done, upon his Principles, ſo far as it reaches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:53010:11"/>
But the beſt way to know whether this were looked upon as a <hi>Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> or not, will be to inquire how the <hi>Irenicum</hi> was received by the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and Regular Clergy. And they, as the Dean aſſures us, <hi>treated him with more kindneſs, than ſo much as to mention any ſuch thing to him, (as a Recantation</hi> &amp;c.) <hi>with reſpect to that unlucky Book,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> had called it. And as to the <hi>Errors and Miſtakes</hi> in it, <hi>They were ſo wiſe to make Allowances for the ſeepticalneſs and injudiciouſneſs of Youth, and for the Prejudices of Education:</hi> As he tells us again, with Decency and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility enough; Though Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> is pleaſed to caſt it often in his Teeth, But I know not why; unleſs it be, that the Modeſty of the expreſſion is very diſagreeable, and a kind of Reproach to a rough and unpoliſhed Humour. But he may uſe him as contemptuouſly as he thinks ſit; yet better Men than he, and of a higher Order, were not aſhamed, a long time ago, to entertain him with more Reſpect. Indeed when the <hi>Irenicum</hi> came abroad, they were exceedingly ſurprized; they could not approve of every thing in the Book, but there was nothing but made them admire the Author. The Project was not only Great, but Good, an attempt to <hi>heal the Wounds</hi> of a miſerable, divided, blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Church. A Deſign ſo vaſt and important, that they could not but wonder, how it ſhould enter the Thoughts of ſo young a Man. And then the Method he purſued for compaſſing the end he had propoſed, though not altogether ſuch as they would have taken, yet it inclined ſo far to the Epiſcopal ſide, as they could ſcarce have expected from one that had been bred up among the Miſts and Confuſions of thoſe diſtracted and unhappy Times. And the whole was proſecuted with that ſubtilty of Argument, that Perſpicuity of ſtyle, and that Variety of Learning, that in theſe reſpects, even at thoſe years, he might have deſerved the Reputation of an Eminent Divine. There were ſome flaſhes of a Juvenile Fancy, which would ſoon be corrected by a riper Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Some Errors there muſt be acknowledged, but commonly of that Sort, which a little further conſideration, would eaſily amend. And the very ſlips and miſtakes that were to be met with, were ſuch as were ſignes of great Ingenuity; and had ſomething mixed with them, that could not but pleaſe thoſe that condemned them. The Book in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed might be compared to one of thoſe Trees that are thick hung with plenty of Fruit, of ſeveral growths; ſome Ripe, ſome Green, ſome in the Bloſſom, and ſome in the Bud; which all together afford a very pleaſant Proſpect, argue an exceeding Luxuriancy and Fertility in the Soil, and may be all brought to perfect maturity in their due time. When the Prudent and Reverend Governours of our Church ſaw the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53010:11"/>
Performance, they looked upon it with Admiration: The Errors they obſerved, which were almoſt hid in the Excellencies of the work, they readily pardoned; and conceived that ſuch Pregnancy of Parts, and accuracy of Learning, which were very diſcernable in that firſt Eſſay of ſo young a Writer, did juſtly deſerve all the incouragement which they could give. And they thought it Pity that thoſe Abilities which had diſcovered themſelves ſo ſoon, and might be improved to the ſingular Advantage of the Church, ſhould not be always imployed upon ſome Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject worthy of them. When therefore the <hi>Anſwer to Arch-Biſhop Laud</hi> came abroad, which was not long after the publication of the <hi>Irenicum,</hi> ſome of them, who had been perſonally known to his Grace, and all of them great ſufferers for their Religion and Loyalty, had ſuch an opinion of Mr. <hi>Stillingſleet,</hi> that they made choice of him to undertake the Defence of the <hi>Conference with</hi> Fiſher. Which he ſet about, and diſpatcht in a few Months, with that ſucceſs, that a very Grave and Learned Prelate thought fit to honour it with a Licence under his own Hand. And it was afterwards entertained with general appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation; and I do not ſee what there is in it to be deſpiſed, or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villed at by Mr. <hi>Lowth.</hi> However it is plain that thoſe Reverend Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, at whoſe deſire he undertook the Work, had great confidence of his Skill and Ability to manage a Controverſie of that moment and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence; and he did not deceive their expectation in the Performance. He acquitted himſelf ſo well in thoſe weighty Diſputes they had inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him in, that they could not but have a very particular reſpect and eſteem for him, which has been conſtantly maintained by thoſe of their Order ever ſince. And if he ſtood ſo fair in their good opinion, when he had ſo lately publiſhed the <hi>Irenicum,</hi> this manifeſtly declares that they were not then ſo angry with the Book, nor with him for Writing it, as Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> was pleaſed to be, above twenty year after.</p>
            <p>I will therefore, as I promiſed, conſider his judgement about it by it ſelf. And what he thought of it when it firſt came out, I cannot tell; and it matters not much what ever it were. But that he might not be accuſed for doing any thing raſhly, when he had pawſed upon the buſineſs, almoſt as many years as the Dean was old when he wrote <hi>that unlucky Book,</hi> out he ſends a very fierce Epiſtle, and peremptorily demands <hi>a Publick Recantation;</hi> and when he had been gently reflected on for that, he ſeconds it with this other long Letter, which I have before me. You ſee the matter was a great while a Brewing. He ſuffered his Choller to boyl inwardly ſo long, without giving it any
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53010:12"/>
vent, that I fear it was become a little Aduſt; but now I hope ſince the plentiful Evacuation it has had in theſe angry Letters, he may be grown more treatable, and not ſo apt to break out into uncivil and paſſionate Expreſſions. For truly all the while he was writing, he ſeems in a mighty wrath at the poor <hi>Irenicum.</hi> And what, do you think, ſhould be the reaſon, that he, above all men, ſhould have ſuch a particular quarrel againſt it? The Biſhops, you know, and all the Clergy, for ought that I could ever hear, though they could not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of the whole, yet they were never ſo highly diſpleaſed, but that they could pardon the miſtakes that were in it. And it was a very long time before Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> himſelf took any notice of them; Twenty year, as I have told you at leaſt; now if he did really think the Book ſo very miſchievous, as he at laſt pretended; why did he not make his Animadverſions upon it any ſooner? if he did not; wherefore did he publiſh them at all? Or if he did verily believe that the <hi>Iremcum</hi> was ſuch a pernicious Treatiſe, and might be of ſuch dangerous inſluence, as he would ſeem to apprehend; what wiſe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe could it ſerve to revive the memory of it, when it was laid out of moſt men's hands, and in a manner forgotten? But I am not to anſwer for the prudence, or Honeſty of the Action: I will only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you with the myſtery of the buſineſs, why He, of all men in the World, ſhould concern himſelf ſo zealouſly about it. And I will ſhew it you from his own words; for when he had mentioned that, <note place="margin">Pag. 12.</note> and ſome other things which he liked as well: <hi>All this,</hi> ſays he, <hi>might make a greater impreſſion upon me, than on ſome others:</hi> And why ſo, I pray? <hi>Becauſe I had for ſome years applyed my Studies to ſearch after the Rights of the Church, &amp;c.</hi> And what then? Had no body elſe done the ſame, had none of the Biſhops, or Clergy of the Nation bent their minds that way? He does not tell us: Or if he will allow they had; either it ſeems, they were not ſubject to ſuch ſad impreſſions, as he was; or elſe they had not ſo deep an inſight into the matter. They could not diſcover the <hi>Deſign</hi> as he did; The deſperate <hi>Deſign</hi> that was moſt cunningly laid, to ruine the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by ſhewing the People that it was certainly Lawful, and, in ſome caſes, neceſſary to ſubmit to the Epiſcopal Power. This is all the formidable Plot, that I can ſee, which provoked him ſo much, and put him in ſuch a fright, that he ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines we are ſcarce out of danger of it yet.</p>
            <p>But let us ſee what we may indeed ſuppoſe to have been the real <hi>Deſign</hi> of this <hi>Irenicum,</hi> we are contending about. And the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter may be brought to a very ſhort Iſſue. There are but two <hi>Deſigns</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:53010:12"/>
that can be tolerably pretended, the one is the Dean's own, the other Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> has made for him. The Dean had ſolemnly profeſſed, at the Writing of it, that his <hi>Deſign was to heal the wounds of the Church:</hi> and he tells us again very lately, in the <hi>Two-penny Paper that is tacked to one of his Four-penny Sermons, that he did adventure to Publiſh it, hoping by that means to bring over thoſe to a compliance with the Church of England, (then like to be Re-eſtabliſhed) who ſtood off upon the ſuppoſition, that Chriſt had appointed a Presbyterian Government to be always continued in his Church; and therefore they thought Prelacy was to be deteſted as an unlawful <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And to the ſame purpoſe elſewhere. This he, which knew beſt, often aſſures us was his <hi>Deſign,</hi> and in my mind it was not an ill one. This Mr. <hi>Lowth,</hi> out of a wonderful Sagacity, in ſpying out <hi>Deſigns,</hi> flatly denys, and like a Man of mettle, tells the Dean roundly, that <hi>He ſhall make it appear, that the account he gives of his Irenicum is not fair, nor true; and that he conceals his crime in the very confeſſion of it: The</hi> whole <hi>Deſign and Plot being</hi> in one place <hi>meerly,</hi> in another <hi>moſtly, if not altogether againſt the Re-eſtabliſhment of the Church of England.</hi> 'T was moſt bravely offered indeed, at the beginning. But what makes him falter ſo ſoon? How comes <hi>meerly</hi> to be turned into <hi>moſtly,</hi> and <hi>moſtly</hi> very near into <hi>Meerly</hi> again, with an <hi>If not?</hi> What is the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this ſtaggering ſo ſtrangely? This uncertainty in preſſing home the main Charge, argues that the Caſe is not very clear. He muſt be conſcious to himſelf of ſomething more than ordinary, when ſuch a Bold mans heart begins to fail him. Well! But here you have two very different <hi>Deſigns,</hi> as can well be imagined; and now which of theſe do you take to be the true one? Or, which is the ſame queſtion in effect, which do you think, the Dean, or Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> was moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly acquainted with the real deſign and occaſion of writing the <hi>Irenicum?</hi> The one aſſirms upon his own certain Knowledge that he intended to ſerve the Church; the other advances a few feeble inſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant Conjectures to prove, that whatever he ſays, his meaning muſt be to overthrow it. And I think this Caſe may be eaſily decided betwixt them, by any indifferent Judge. For unleſs the Dean's Credit and Reputation be quite for feited, which Malice it ſelf dares not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, there is no reaſon but that we ſhould take his word. His poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and repeated Aſſertion of a thing, which no man in the World can know ſo well as he, muſt needs outweigh Mr. <hi>Lowth's</hi> groundleſs and uncharitable ſuſpicion, in a matter, of which he can never be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured. There is no Compariſon in the <hi>Evidenc<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and if Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> were of the Jury, he muſt bring in a Verdict againſt himſelf. But yet
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53010:13"/>
that he may not complain of Partiality, I will briefly examine the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Plea that he makes. The grand Principle which ran through the whole Diſcourſe, he is ſo angry at, is this, <hi>That Chriſt had not appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any unalterable form of Government in his Church.</hi> This is acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it was an Errour; and be it ſo: Yet how does it from hence ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that the <hi>Deſign</hi> was either <hi>meerly</hi> or <hi>moſtly againſt the Re-eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church of England?</hi> All that he offers in proof of this, is his <hi>Denying Epiſcopacy to be by the Laws-of Chriſt always binding and imuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;</hi> and that he attributes too much <hi>Power to the Civil Magiſtrate</hi> in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs. This will be freely confeſſed; and yet the <hi>Deſign</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 25.</note> he ſpeaks of, cannot be rightly gathered from it. And to convince him that his Argument will not hold, we will turn the Tables: And let us ſuppoſe then for once, without offence, that Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> had been a Zealous <hi>Presbyterian;</hi> then becauſe the <hi>Irenicum</hi> denyes that <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> to be <hi>immutable,</hi> as well as the <hi>Epiſcopal;</hi> and gives away ſome of the <hi>Power</hi> to the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate,</hi> which is wont to be aſſumed by their <hi>Claſſical</hi> and <hi>Synodical</hi> Aſſemblies; he might have made the very <note place="margin">Pag. 40.</note> ſame Complaints in favour of the <hi>Conſiſtory;</hi> and turned the <hi>Deſign</hi> quite another way, and ſaid it had been <hi>meerly or moſtly, if not altogether againſt the</hi> ſettlement <hi>of the Church of Geneva.</hi> This he might have done with as much reaſon, as what he did: For I do not ſee where the Diſparity lyes. And you know he that proves too much, proves nothing. That Argument can never be good that will ſerve the Plaintif as well as the Defendant; and may be urged with equal force on both ſides. 'Tis like a mans ſlouriſhing his Weapon, with <hi>a here I could have you,</hi> and <hi>there I could have you.</hi> I will not call it ridiculous; but for all that, it is nothing better than an idle kind of skirmiſhing with the Air. But it is not only evident that the <hi>Deſign</hi> of the <hi>Irenicum</hi> may be as eaſily levelled againſt the <hi>Prerbyterian,</hi> as the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Church; but if the Dean's word, who only could certainly know his own <hi>deſign,</hi> were not ſufficient; yet if you pleaſe to peruſe the Book, you will find ſo many things ſpoken there to the advantage of it, that would be enough of themſelves to incline any unprejudiced man to believe, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the Author was indeed, <hi>To bring over Diſſenters to a complyance with the Church of England.</hi> Nay, this is ſo very obvious, that Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> himſelf could not avoid being ſenſible of it. For after he had taken a great deal of pains to lay open the Dean's <hi>Deſign,</hi> as he would have it; he concludes that part of his Letter in a wonderful Heat, calls all his Rhetorick together, and aggravates the matter very Tragically; and that untoward <hi>Irenicum</hi> he tells us; <hi>It is a Hotch-potch or mixture <note place="margin">Pag. 5.</note>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:53010:13"/>
of all Religions—I may ſafely ſay, It has perverted many Thouſands, (ſhould I add Millions, I did not exceed.)</hi> A very ſad thing really! <hi>Millions!</hi> But don't you think there may be ſomething of the <hi>Hyperbole</hi> here? He ſays he <hi>did not exceed,</hi> but I hope, he was miſtaken. But he goes on ſtill: <hi>It is the very Center of Puritaniſme, and Epitome of Fanatick madneſs.</hi> Mighty Lofty, indeed! But the unhappineſs of it is, that as ſoon as ever he had ended this warm Declamation, he overturns it all immediately by an unlucky ſuppoſition: <hi>If it be objected.</hi> What? <hi>that you have in ſome particular paſſages of this Book, declared your ſelf in a different manner than is here repreſented.</hi> Why? Are there any ſuch <hi>Paſſages</hi> in that <hi>very Center,</hi> that <hi>Epitome of Fanatick madneſs?</hi> What was the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon then, that they were all ſmothered? What <hi>Deſign</hi> was there in that? <hi>Nothing but the purſuit of Truth and Honeſty,</hi> to be ſure. For he picks out whatever he thinks is for his purpoſe, and ſlyly paſſes over what he pleaſes. And when he has by this means mangled the Diſcourſe, he makes moſt paſſionate Invectives againſt the horrible miſchievous <hi>Deſign</hi> of it; and when the guilt of this falſe, and unjuſt Dealing ſlyes in his Face; he indeavours to palliate all, and put it off with a ſlight Evaſion, and only ſaying: <hi>I anſwer, My buſineſs is not to reconcile every contradiction in your Book: That were impoſſible</hi> he thinks. But though I verily believe indeed, his <hi>Buſineſs was not to Reconcile Contradictions,</hi> or any thing elſe; yet certainly it was his <hi>Buſineſs</hi> to give a fair and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial account of the whole matter; and not to lay together the worſt he could find on one ſide, and conceal every thing that had been ſaid on the Other. Now becauſe he has done this, by his own Confeſſion; I leave it to you to Judge which is the moſt probable: That the <hi>Deſign</hi> was for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as the Dean profeſſes; or againſt it, as Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> pretends; and ſeems reſolved to maintain, Right or Wrong.</p>
            <p>But whatever your Opinion be of the <hi>Deſign</hi> of the <hi>Irenicum,</hi> or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever any one may ſuppoſe it was; Let us now ſee whether the Dean hath not ſince given ſufficient <hi>Satisfaction</hi> for any material <hi>Errors</hi> and <hi>Miſtakes</hi> that might be in it. This Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> imagines he has not, and this I will indeavour to ſhew the Dean has effectually done. To this, purpoſe it will be neceſſary to inquire, what <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> will be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? I anſwer, in Mr. <hi>Lowths</hi> words, it muſt be <hi>A Recantation as pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick as the Errour, Scandal, and Offence.</hi> This I ſay had been done a conſiderable time, before ever that Imperious Demand was made. For that was in Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi>'s firſt Letter of <hi>May</hi> the firſt 83. and the excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable Paſſages of the <hi>Irenicum</hi> had been formally retracted in a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53010:14"/>
Book that was Licenſed, <hi>May</hi> the ſixth 79. It conſiſts of <hi>ſeveral Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences;</hi> and when the Romiſh Prieſt had put the Queſtion, in one of them: <hi>What ſay you to his Irenicum, in the firſt place?</hi> The Dean, under the Perſon of the Proteſtant Divine, replies thus: <hi>I will tell you freely; I believe there are many things in it, which if Dr.</hi> Stillingfleet <hi>were to write</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Several Conf. p. 148. 149.</note> 
               <hi>now, he would not have ſaid: For there are ſome things which ſhew his Youth, and want of due conſideration: Others which he yielded too far, in hopes of gaining the diſſenting Parties to the Church of</hi> England; <hi>but upon the whole matter, I am fully ſacisfied, the Book was written with a deſign to ſerve the Church of</hi> England. <hi>And the deſign of it, I take to be this; that among us there was no neceſſity of entring upon nice and ſubtle diſputes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a ſtrict</hi> Jus Divinum <hi>of Epiſcopacy, ſuch as makes all other Forms of Government unlawful; but it was ſufficient for us, if it were prov'd to be the moſt ancient, and agreeable to Apoſtolial practice, and moſt accommodate to our Laws, and Civil Government; and there could be no pretence againſt ſubmitting to it, but the demonſtrating its unlawfulneſs, which he knew was impoſſible to be done. And for what propoſals he makes about tempering Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy, they were no other than what King</hi> Charles <hi>1ſt. and Mr.</hi> Thorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dike <hi>had made before him; and doth</hi> T. G. <hi>think they deſigned to ruine the Church of</hi> England? <hi>And as long as he declared this to be the deſign of his Book, both at the beginning and concluſion of it, ſuppoſe he were miſtaken in the means he took, muſt ſuch a Man be preſently condemned, as one that ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at the Ruine and Deſtruction of the Church?</hi> This place is ſo clear and remarkable; that I wonder how it could eſcape Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi>'s no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice. I have tranſcribed it intire as it lyes; becauſe it contains a general <hi>Recantation</hi> of whatever was amiſs in the <hi>Irenicum.</hi> For here the Dean frankly acknowledges, <hi>There are many things in it which if he were to write now, he would not have ſaid:</hi> That <hi>there are ſome things which ſhew his Youth, and want of due conſideration: Others which he yielded too far.</hi> This is a free and open Confeſſion, and as much, I think, as could be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably expected. Then he confirms, what I have ſhewed already, that the <hi>Deſign was to ſerve the Church of</hi> England: And he indeavours to excuſe the <hi>Miſtakes</hi> of it upon that account. For what he had mentioned about <hi>tempering Epiſcopacy;</hi> he defends it by the Authority of <hi>King Charles 1ſt.</hi> and Mr. <hi>Thorndike.</hi> The words of King <hi>Charles</hi> he repeats again in the Epiſtle Dedicatory to My Lord of <hi>London;</hi> they are for the <hi>Reducing Epiſcopacy, and Presbytery to ſuch a well-proportioned Form of Superiority and ſubordination, as may beſt reſemble the Apoſtolical and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times.</hi> Theſe words Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> takes no notice of, but ſeems ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream <note place="margin">Pag. 55. 56.</note> Angry, tells the Dean he <hi>had ſlandered all our Princes and Biſhops
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53010:14"/>
ſince the Reformation,</hi> &amp;c. and that his <hi>Friends of the Presbytery cannot take it well at his hands, that he ſhould attempt to perſwade the World, they brought that Glorious Martyr to the Block for being a Presbyterian.</hi> It is hard to imagine what ſhould make a Man talk at ſuch an extravagant rate. If the Words be in the Paper, as they are, then they can be no <hi>Slander,</hi> whatever they be. And how can they ever make their Royal Author a <hi>Presbyterian;</hi> when they expreſly mention <hi>a ſuperiority, and ſubordination,</hi> which directly overthrows the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Party, which is the very Life and Soul of that Government? But if he pleaſe to inquire further into the matter, I believe he will find that King <hi>Charles,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Thorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dike,</hi> and the Dean too, meant no more, but that the <hi>Biſhops</hi> retaining all their Antient Rights, the <hi>Presbyters</hi> ſhould be admitted of their Council, whoſe Advice and concurrence might be had in ſome Caſes. This is very conſiſtent with the Practice of the firſt Ages; and this I take to be the ſame that is by Law eſtabliſhed in our Church. For in the Execution of ſome parts of the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Power, the Aſſiſtance of <hi>Presbyters</hi> is required; and the Canons and Conſtitutions, by which the <hi>Biſhops</hi> Govern, are to be paſſed in both Houſes of Convocation, as well in the Lower, where are none but <hi>Presbyters,</hi> as in the Upper, where the <hi>Biſhops</hi> only have Right to ſit. And let this be, as Mr. <hi>Lowth thinks, from a particular Law of this Kingdom;</hi> however it is Ours. And <note place="margin">Pag 74.</note> if he had thought of it, he might have made the Church of <hi>England Presbyterians;</hi> upon the ſame reaſon that he pretends the Dean had done King <hi>Charles,</hi> for that paſſage he cited from him. This therefore is not yet <hi>Recanted,</hi> but <hi>yielding too far,</hi> in ſome other Points, is. And beſides this, in the very Epiſtle which occaſion'd the Letter we are now conſidering, there is an acknowledgment of <hi>Errors and Miſtakes that were in it [the Irenicum]</hi> And we are told that our <hi>Superiors in the Church were ſo wiſe to make allowances for the ſcepticalneſs and Injudiciouſneſs of Youth, and for the Prejudices of Education.</hi> Where there is a <hi>Recantation</hi> manifeſtly implyed again. But this as well as the former, will not be regarded, nor ever thought upon; unleſs it be to twit him now and then with the modeſty of the Expreſſions; which is a Crime Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> may be ſecured, can never be charged upon Him.</p>
            <p>But having paſſed over theſe, and ſome other places, it may be, which look the ſame way, he inſiſts ſtifly upon three things, for which, he would perſwade us, the Dean has made no <hi>ſatisfaction:</hi> The <hi>Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript,</hi> the <hi>Powers of Church Officers,</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi> I will do him the Right to inquire a little further into every one of them.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Manuſcript,</hi> there has been ſome Controverſie already
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53010:15"/>
about it; and in this Letter Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> ſeems inraged at it. He calls it a <hi>Vagrant, illegitimate Script;</hi> and in one place, <hi>your counterfeit Manuſcript:</hi> But he does not offer any thing conſiderable, to make it appear to be ſo. <note place="margin">Pag. 57.</note> And if he could have proved the ſorgery, and ſhewn the Dean to have been <note place="margin">Pag. 59.</note> guilty of it; I ſuppoſe he is ſo honeſt and juſt a man, he would never have ſpared him. But becauſe he cannot accuſe him of any falſe dealing in the Caſe, I do not ſee what <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> he can be obliged to give for a Paper, of which he cannot be pretended to have been the Author. Some part of it was publiſhed in the <hi>Irenicum,</hi> but without any alteration from the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal writing. The whole was ſet forth afterwards by Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> in <note place="margin">Part. 2. c. 7</note> his <hi>Collection of Records:</hi> and if he varied no more from his Copy, than the Dean had done, he cannot be juſtly blamed. But that ſhall be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined <note place="margin">Book 3. N. 21.</note> preſently. In the mean time it is not ſtrange that <hi>Cranmer,</hi> and ſome others ſhould fall into ſome <hi>Errors</hi> in the matter of <hi>Church Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi> For the Controverſie about it, was but then newly ſtarted, and could not be ſo fully enquired into, as it has been ſince; and the Opinion of the Schools concerning <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> had been ſo looſe, and the Queſtion of the <hi>Supremacy</hi> ſo warmly debated; that it can be no wonder if they were unacquainted with ſomething that was the <hi>Biſhops</hi> Right, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed as much to the King, as ever had been uſurped by the <hi>Pope.</hi> But whatever their <hi>Miſtakes</hi> might be, they who put out the <hi>Manuſcript,</hi> wherein they were contained, were bound to publiſh it as it was, not as we could have wiſhed it had been. But this Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> averrs was not done; for <hi>I muſt tell you plainly,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I have not met with a more notorious Artifice, and palpable abuſe, in all my reading; unleſs I except that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 63.</note> 
               <hi>of the Pope's Legates in the Council of Carthage, for the Adulterating of the Nicene Canons.</hi> The Crime you ſee, is very heynous, but he had endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to make it out before; for ſpeaking of the Dean and the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcript,</hi> he has theſe words. <hi>You and Dr.</hi> Burnet <hi>are not diſcharged, but ſtand accuſed of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithfulneſs, and underhand Dealing in the Printing and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 60.</note> 
               <hi>Publiſhing of it; and that upon theſe two accounts.</hi> 1. <hi>For altering the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral method of it.</hi> 2. <hi>For leaving out Biſhop</hi> Cranmer<hi>'s Subſcription to Dr.</hi> Leighton's <hi>Opinion concerning Church Power, by which he retracted his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Erroneous Judgment.</hi> This is the Charge that is drawn up, and vehemently urged againſt the Dean, and Dr. <hi>Burnet;</hi> I will tell you how far I think the Whole, or any part of it may be made good againſt Both, or either of them.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing for which they both <hi>Stand accuſed of unfaithfulneſs, and under-hand-dealing, is, for altering the general method of the Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript.</hi> But if there be any <hi>unfaithfulneſs or under-hand-Dealing</hi> in this,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53010:15"/>
the Dean is innocent of it; for I am certainly informed he adviſed the contrary; that all ſhould be Printed juſt as it lay in the Papers. He foreſaw, I conceive, that otherwiſe, though the thing imported very little, yet quarrelſome Spirits might take occaſion to cavil at it. This notwithſtanding in the Publication, Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> adventures to put the whole in another order; but then he gives his reaſon why he did it: <hi>He judged it might be more acceptable to the Reader to ſee every man's An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer ſet down after every Queſtion:</hi> Whereas in the <hi>Manuſcript,</hi> which was nothing but the very Original Papers gathered up and Bound to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, their Anſwers to every Queſtion lay ſcattered in every man's particular Paper. But leaſt this digeſting them into a more uſeful <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod</hi> as he thought, ſhould breed any miſtake; after their Reſolutions of the Seventeenth, which is the laſt Queſtion, he ſets the Names of the Biſhops and Divines, as they themſelves had done, with this Note in the Margent: <hi>Theſe are the Subſcriptions which are at the end of every Man's Paper.</hi> And what is there in this that can deſerve to be ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely condemned? There is not the change of any one word pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; and the <hi>Alteration</hi> that was made in the <hi>Method,</hi> was deſigned for the <hi>Reader's</hi> convenience; and moſt men think it was ſo; but if any like the old <hi>Method,</hi> or rather want of <hi>Method</hi> better, there are plain Directions, whereby all may be eaſily reduced to that again. However there can be no <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithfulneſs, nor under-hand-dealing</hi> here, where every thing is ſairly, and freely acknowledged He would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have diſcovered himſelf ſo openly, if his intent had been to put a Cheat upon the World. But this is the ſlighteſt part of the accuſation, and Mr. <hi>Lowth,</hi> I preſume, will not lay any ſtreſs upon it.</p>
            <p>The other is far more Conſiderable, <hi>That they have left out Biſhop Cranmer's Subſcription to Dr. Leighton's Opinion concerning Church-Power, by which he retracted his former Erroneous Judgment.</hi> This indeed were a very foul thing, and if it could be proved, would leave both the Dean and Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> without any excuſe. For this we are told that the <hi>Arch-Biſhop ſubſcribed to Dr. Leighton's Opinion with his own hand, ſetting</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> Th. Canturarienſis <hi>below the Doctors, and blotting out his firſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription. You,</hi> ſays he, <hi>have wholly omitted this.</hi> Here are no leſs three miſtakes in theſe few words; one that the <hi>Arch Biſhops</hi> Name was put <hi>below Dr. Leighton's,</hi> whereas it was not ſet under it, but by the ſide, in the Margent of the Paper: Another that he <hi>Blotted out his firſt Subſcription,</hi> when it remains to this Day as Legible as any of the reſt: And the Third, <hi>thas all this was wholly omitted;</hi> whereas the <hi>Arch-Biſhops</hi> Name is <hi>Subſcribed</hi> as often in the Print, as it is in the Original. A
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53010:16"/>
little farther he makes a fourth miſtake in the ſame matter, for he ſuppoſes that <hi>Cranmer's Subſcription was under Leighton's,</hi> to the Article <hi>Concerning Church Power,</hi> which is the place where he complains it is <hi>Omitted;</hi> whereas neither <hi>Cranmer's</hi> nor <hi>Leighton's Subſcription</hi> was put immediately to that Article, or any other, but only to the Laſt, which muſt be underſtood to have been done in confirmation of all the reſt, as well as that; and there both their Names are ſtill to be ſeen in Dr. <hi>Burnet's</hi> Printed Collection. How many voluntary miſtakes does he run into, that he may accuſe his Adverſaries of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithfulneſs,</hi> when by that very attempt, he makes himſelf guilty of it in in a very high degree. But yet he will plead they have heen <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithful</hi> too; becauſe they have not acquainted the World with <hi>Cranmer's Retractation</hi> of his former Opinion. To this it may be replyed, that if <hi>Cranmer's Subſcription</hi> to <hi>Leighton's</hi> Paper did imply ſuch a <hi>Retractation,</hi> then they have acquainted the World with it, by the publication of that <hi>Subſcription;</hi> if it did not, then it was well done, not to impoſe upon the World, as he would have them, by falſe Gloſſes, and forced In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations. But did not <hi>Cranmer retract his firſt Opinion</hi> then? with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt he did. Why then was this <hi>wholly omitted?</hi> whatever Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> may pretend, it was not. Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> had given an expreſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it, in the proper place, as he knows; and uſed a more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing argument to prove it, than that <hi>Subſcription,</hi> in the very Page wherein he refers to the Record we are contending about. His words are theſe. <hi>In Cranmer's Paper ſome ſingular opinions of his about</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hiſt. R<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f. Book 1ſt.</note> 
               <hi>the Nature of Eccleſiaſtical Offices will be found; but as they are delivered by him with all poſſible modeſty; So they were not eſtabliſhed as the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church, but laid aſide as particular conceits of his own, and it ſeems that afterward he CHANGED his opinion. For he Subſcribed the Bock that was ſoon after ſet out; which is directly contrary to thoſe Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions ſet down in theſe Papers.</hi> This paſſage Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> could not be ignorant of; but he cunningly ſlides over it, becauſe he ſaw it was not for his purpoſe. And this I think may be enough to ſhew that <hi>Cranmer's Subſcription to Leighton's</hi> Paper was not <hi>omitted;</hi> nor his <hi>Retractation</hi> otherwiſe concealed.</p>
            <p>But indeed it was not any thing of this nature that was the real ground of the quarrel; it is the bare Publiſhing of the <hi>Manuſcript</hi> that ſeems to have made Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> ſo angry; he would have had it otherwiſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſed of; and he inſinuates his mind in a Story out of <hi>Livy,</hi> which he thus relates: <hi>In the ground of Petilius the Scribe, were found two Cheſts, the one had a bundle in it containing Seven Books in Latine, de <note place="margin">Pag. 60.</note>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:53010:16"/>
jure Pontificio, or relating to Religious matters; they were peruſed by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and, at laſt, read to the Senators, who, immediately condemned them to the Fire, (and they were accordingly burnt before the People) becauſe in many things tending to the diſſolution of their Religion.</hi> This is a way of procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, would have fitted the Conclave, as well as it did the Senate. 'Tis probable, that City has been under the Influence of the ſame cautious Planet from the very beginning; but I did not think before, that the way of dealing with Heretical <hi>Manuſcripts</hi> could have been proved by ſuch ancient Tradition. Well! but what thinks Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> of this? Why, he admires it much, and eſteems it a choice Example of an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Prudence. For ſo he goes on: <hi>The Wiſdom of that Government knew full well the ill conſequences of admitting ſuch looſer Papers into compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition with their received Worſhip,</hi> &amp;c. But I hope their Caſe and ours are ſomething different. A falſe Religion may have reaſon to be jealous of all Oppoſition, and do that by <hi>Fire,</hi> which it cannot by Argument; but the true One has no need to be ſo extreamly apprehenſive of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. It knows it ſelf to be built upon ſo firm a Foundation, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be eaſily ſhaken; and therefore it is not afraid of what can be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt it. Whatever others may be forced to do, the Church of <hi>England</hi> has no occaſion for any unwarrantable Artifice to ſupport it ſelf; we are not put to a neceſſity of forging, or ſuppreſſing any Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings to maintain our Cauſe. We do deſervedly retain a very great Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration for Arch-Biſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> but we do not think we can ſuffer ſo much by any private Opinion of his, that we ſhould be tempted to Deſtroy his Papers, for the ſake of that; eſpecially when it was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed with ſo much Dubiouſneſs, and deliberately <hi>Retracted</hi> not very long after. And when all is done, I am verily perſwaded, that the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are better ſatisfied to ſee the <hi>Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript</hi> Publiſhed as it is; than if it had been <hi>Burnt,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> adviſes very gravely, like a <hi>Roman Senator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next thing wherein he imagines the Dean has not given ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> is <hi>The Power of Church-Officers.</hi> And to make this out, he undertakes to examine ſome of his Books, where he might have found many things that way, which he thinks fit to take no notice of; and for what he has choſen out, he very often either miſtakes, or elſe wilfully perverts the ſenſe. Sometimes 'tis pleaſant to ſee how he will be Tutor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Pag. 66.</note> the Dean, and ſhewing him how he ſhould have <hi>expreſſed himſelf.</hi> But I muſt not trouble you with ſuch Obſervations as theſe; that were <note place="margin">Pag. 64.</note> an Argument too Copious. The firſt Treatiſe he pitches upon, is the <hi>Appendix to the Irenicum;</hi> where he acknowledges the <hi>Arguments for
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53010:17"/>
Church-Power are common, but good:</hi> This is a very kind conceſſion for Him. But then the exception is, that this is <hi>limited to the Power of Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication.</hi> Why, then that was <hi>Competently well done, ſo far.</hi> And that was the Subject to be treated of, and to have extended it farther, in that place, had been little to the purpoſe. And the Dean, I believe, can hardly be ſorry yet, that he was not impertinent; though that it ſhould ſeem, had been the only way to have pleaſed Mr. <hi>Lowth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Treatiſe he falls upou, is <hi>The Vindication of Arch-Biſhop Lawd,</hi> the ſame which he thinks might have <hi>diſcompoſed him upon the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 65.</note> 
               <hi>Scaffold, if he could hve been aware of it;</hi> and it is not ſtrange, if all be true which he ſays; <hi>In which I ſind little amends for theſe your Irenicum Doctrines; but rather, an evident confirmation of many of them, if not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worſe.</hi> That muſt be very bad indeed, at leaſt in his eſteem; but then the wonder is, that none of theſe very ill things ſhould be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by the Reverend Prelate that licenſed the Book; who in his time was taken for as Wiſe and Learned a Man, as Mr. <hi>Lowth,</hi> and had cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly done and ſuffered as much forthe Church. Nay, beſides this publick approbation of ſo eminent a Perſon, and other acknowledgments, which ſome of his Graces near and Learned Relations thought ſit to make, all the Biſhops of that time were pleaſed to give the Dean their particular thanks for the Work: An Honour, I believe, that has not yet been confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon the Author of this Letter; and which does ſufficiently ſigniſie how different their apprehenſions were from His. But an extraordinary Good-will is extreamly ſagacious; and by the help of this, Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> has been inabled to ſpy out more, than any man before him could do. After a diligent ſearch in that large Volume, he has happened upon a little piece of a ſentence, which he conceits has a very ill Aſpect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Church-Power.</hi> And it is this: <hi>The being of a Chureh, ſuppoſes this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent belief [or aſſent to the Doctrine of Chriſt] in Chriſtians.</hi> This is <note place="margin">Pag. 66.</note> no ſuch Paradox, but that, 'tis likely, a far meaner man than the Dean might be able to defend it. But he, when he has been at ſome pains to miſunderſtand it, loads it with no leſs than five and twenty of the moſt monſtrous Conſequences, that he could think of; and at the ſame rate, a man of ſuch a fruitful Imagination as He is, might have eaſily increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the number to five and forty more; and after all, he gives up the Cauſe, by <hi>yielding, that Believers, in ſome ſenſe, are antecedent to the Church.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 69.</note> Which is a Propoſition ſo very like that for which he quarrels the Dean, that the moſt, if not all the Objections that are made againſt the one, may be returned with equal force upon the other; and, as he explains himſelf, not without the Addition of ſome peculiar Difficulties upon
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:53010:17"/>
Him. But I will not inſiſt upon them, becauſe I cannot perceive how either of the Opinions can be deſtructive of <hi>Church-Power;</hi> ſince it is a part of the <hi>Antecedent Belief,</hi> which is granced on both ſides, that there is a <hi>Church,</hi> and that it is the duty of every one to unite him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf unto it, and to be obedient to the Governours of it.</p>
            <p>The Dean in his <hi>Anſwer to ſever al Treatiſes</hi> has reduced the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity <note place="margin">Anſwer to ſeveral Treat. p. 267, &amp;c.</note> of the Governours of the Church to theſe three Heads: 1. <hi>An Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of inflicting Cenſures upon Offenders; which is commonly called the Power of the Keys, or of receiving into, and excluding out of the Communion of the Church.</hi> 2. <hi>An Authority of making Rules and Canons about matters of Order and Decency in the Church.</hi> 3. <hi>An Authority of propoſing matters of Faith, and directing Men in Religion.</hi> If you pleaſe, you may ſee in that place, how every one of theſe is farther explained; the paſſage is ſo expreſs, and ſo very appoſite to the matter in diſpute, that Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> could by no means wholly avoid it. But he ſtrives to hide the Evidence of it, as much as may be; he only refers to the Pages where it is, but dares not truſt the Reader with the ſight of one word of it; for fear he ſhould be convinced, by ſo clear a Teſtimony, that the Dean's opinion of the <hi>Authority of the Church,</hi> was ſound and Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox. Therefore, without mentioning what had been ſaid, he puts in a blind exception to the whole in groſs, and affirms conſidently, that notwithſtanding all the Dean had ſpoken in this place, yet he <hi>Has left the Church without Power to make her Declarations Law.</hi> But this he <note place="margin">Pag. 76.</note> does not ſo much as attempt to prove. I wiſh he had; for it is plain that here is an <hi>Authority</hi> to Command attributed to the <hi>Church,</hi> and a <hi>Power</hi> to inforce her Commands by inflicting of <hi>Cenſures</hi> upon all thoſe that will not obey; and if this be not enough to make a <hi>Law,</hi> I ſhould be glad to be informed what is. But the <hi>Authority of making Rules and Canons about matters of Order and Decency</hi> was ſo plainly aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that there was no denying of it; yet he tryes to ſhift it off, by ſaying, that <hi>it is no more, in effect, than what had been ſaid before in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 77.</note> 
               <hi>the Irenicum:</hi> and ſuppoſe it be; what then? That does not any way leſſen what is ſaid here; but only ſhew that the very <hi>Irenicum</hi> it ſelf, by his own confeſſion, is nothing ſo bad a Book, nor ſuch an irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable Enemy to <hi>Church. Power</hi> as he would make it.</p>
            <p>Upon this he ſtarts out of the way, if he were ever in, and runs into a Digreſſion full of nothing but vain ſurmiſes little to the purpoſe, and never returns to the buſineſs in hand, till he comes to the <hi>Treatiſe of the unreaſonableneſs of Separation;</hi> and that he allows to be <hi>Competently well done, ſo far as it reaches,</hi> as I have told you before; but then leaſt <note place="margin">Pag. 78.</note>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:53010:18"/>
any thing of the Dean's ſhould eſcape without a mark of his diſpleaſure; he thinks that <hi>All is left ſtill as matter of Diſpute, &amp;c.</hi> But that I have ſhewed already is not ſo; and that there is an obligation to Obedience laid upon the Subject. And whoſoever ſhall peruſe that whole Diſcourſe, without Prejudice, muſt certainly be convinced that the Dean has given abundant <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> for any former <hi>Miſtakes</hi> about <hi>Church-Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt thing is <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> and here the Charge is but ſhort, but it is very vehement and pathetical. <hi>You have made no ſatisfaction at all to the Church of God, for that Irenicum Doctrine, which equals the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 83.</note> with the <hi>Biſhop.</hi> What? None <hi>at all?</hi> No: <hi>There is not any thing like amends for it in all your Writings that I have met with.</hi> Then I gueſs there may be ſome which have not yet fallen into his hands. But let us ſee what he has <hi>met with. It is true, you often ſpeak of Epiſcopacy, as the moſt Antient Government deriveable from the Apoſtles:</hi> Sure this too is <hi>Competently well done, ſo far;</hi> ſomething <hi>like amends,</hi> at leaſt. But what ſhould there be wanting to make it compleat? why this: <hi>You have not any where aſſerted it in the number of thoſe Inſtitutions and Practices</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pag. 84.</note> 
               <hi>Apoſtolical, which are perpetual and immutable: And until you ſay this, all you can ſay beſides is to no purpoſe.</hi> Well, ſince it is reſolved that nothing elſe ſhall ſerve the turn, pray do but look into the Diſcourſe of <hi>the unreaſonableneſs of Separation,</hi> and conſider whether there be not enough ſaid in that Book to make it appear, than it was really the Dean's Opinion that the <hi>Epiſcopal Government</hi> was <hi>unalterable.</hi> Or if this will not ſuffice, I think there is ſomething in the <hi>Two-penny Paper</hi> that may. For in that the Dean tells us, that <hi>He does now think much more is to be ſaid for the Apoſtolical Inſtitution of Epiſcopacy, than he at that time apprehended,</hi> when he wrote the <hi>Irenicum.</hi> Here <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> is acknowledged to be of <hi>Apoſtolical Inſtitution</hi> and that implies it to be <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual and immutable.</hi> For though ſome things of meer <hi>Apoſtolical Practice</hi> may, thoſe that are of <hi>Apoſtolical Inſtitution</hi> cannot be changed: what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they appointed to be obſerved in the Church, no Power upon Earth has Authority to alter. But if this be not enough yet, then I deſire you to conſult the <hi>Four-penny Sermons,</hi> in which Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny ſome <hi>Errors,</hi> which he imputes to the Dean, to have been <hi>Retracted;</hi> and in the beginning of his Letter he very Complementally <hi>Rejoyces,</hi> and <hi>thanks</hi> him for it, <hi>No man more.</hi> But that was ſuddainly ſlipt out of his mind; therefore I will take the liberty to refreſh his <note place="margin">Pag. 3.</note> Memory with a paſſage or two which will clear the matter we are now upon. And beſides the general Scope of a great part of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, in one place he delivers his mind thus: <hi>That the Biſhops did ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dr. Stil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lingfleet's Serm. p. 30.</note> 
               <hi>the Apoſtles, we have the general conſent of the Antient Fathers, who were the moſt competent Witneſſes in this Caſe; which is an Argument they
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:53010:18"/>
believed the Apoſtolical Power, with reſpect to the Government of Churches, did not expire with the Apoſtles, but was to continue, as long as Chriſt had promiſed to be with them,</hi> i. e. <hi>to the end of the World.</hi> And afterwards again: <hi>Our Church hath wiſely and truly determined, that ſince the Apoſtles times there have been three Orders of Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons;</hi> and then he adds, <hi>and in a regular, well conſtituted Church, are to Continue</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ib. Pa. 38.</note> 
               <hi>to the World's end.</hi> Theſe are as full declarations of his Judgement, concerning the <hi>Perpetuity, and immutability of Epiſcopacy,</hi> as can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired; unleſs Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> ſhould conceit that the Church Triumphant is governed by <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and may hope to be made one in the other world. But how the overlooking of theſe, and many things elſe, and inſiſting ſtill upon the old accuſation, as if it had not been clearly anſwered, can comport with his <hi>Deſign of Truth and Honeſty,</hi> is worth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry. I leave it to your thoughts, and hope I have made it plainly appear that the Dean has given very good <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> for all the <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours</hi> and <hi>Miſtakes</hi> that have been laid to his charge.</p>
            <p>This Letter is grown longer than I intended, when I began it, and yet I have taken ſome pains to contract it. For if I had followed Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> in all his Rambles, and remarked every thing that was really exceptionable, it would have been five times the length, and muſt have been Read by you with as little pleaſure, as his was. I have dealt with him as tenderly as I could; and if I have ſaid any thing that may ſeem ſevere, it has been extorted by his unſufferable Rudeneſs to a better Man. Look upon his <hi>Letter</hi> once more, and you will rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily excuſe the hardeſt word I have given him. He takes care to let the World know that his firſt Book was the <hi>Reſult of the Courſe of his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Subject Church Power. Pref.</note> 
               <hi>Studies,</hi> and ſo it might; but this can be the <hi>Reſult,</hi> of nothing but An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and want of Conſideration, and an inveterate kindneſs for his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary. For there is not any thing in it clearly proved, but an untra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable croſſneſs, and an impotent deſire to be Cavilling at every thing the Dean can write. Of this we have had many evidences already, and you may expect more when you ſhall have the happineſs to ſee another choice Piece, with which he is ſometimes threatning the Reader. For he ſeems reſolved to ſignalize himſelf for ever, by ſtill Renewing his bold Attempts upon the Dean of St. <hi>Pauls.</hi> That he ſhould have the Ambition, I do not wonder; but what ſhould give him the Confidence, I cannot certainly tell; only I conjecture there is one thing may have done him ſome harm, and put him upon enterprizing above his ſtrength. You know he pretends to have been very Converſant, in ſome of the beſt Authors; and his Induſtry, for ought I know, might have been commendable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; but then, as 'tis probable, aſſociating himſelf often with ſome
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:53010:19"/>
that had little or no skill in that way, among whom he might ſafely ſwag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger with the great Names, of <hi>Biſhops, Doctors, and Fathers of the Church</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ib.</note> 
               <hi>Catholick, the Church Hiſtorians, Councils, and Laws Imperial</hi> &amp;c. and they ſtand all amazed, and ſtare upon him, and take him for nothing leſs than a perfect Oracle of Antiquity: And, as moſt men are apt to think well of themſelves, this might increaſe the conceit of his own Learning, and make him preſume ſo far, as to Judge himſelfan over-match for the Dean; and there upon write to him with as much aſſurance, as if he had been dictating to his ignorant Admirers over a Diſh of Coffee. He had been ſo uſed to give Law to his Companions, that he imagined all the World would have held their Peace, and gaped at him, as they were Wont. But he was very much deceived, the Generality of men had quite another ſenſe of Things; they were ſomething ſtartled with the firſt, but they were out of all patience at the incomparable Rudeneſs of this ſecond Attack. I am affraid I may incur his diſpleaſure, by the freedom I have taken to remind him of it; but I deſerve his Thanks, for indeavouring to make him ſenſible of thoſe faults, for which he ſtands condemned by all the World. For I am confident there is not ſo much as a Remnant of that little <hi>Party,</hi> which was once carefully fomented, againſt the Dean and ſome others, about <hi>Coſmus Blene,</hi> now remaining; 'tis very likely, they have all deſerted: For ſure they could not be ſo very Weak, but that they muſt plainly ſee, that their mighty Champion has been able to do juſt nothing at laſt, afte all his Huſſing, and Bluſtering for the Cauſe. You cannot eſteem any Expreſſion I have uſed too harſh, when you reflect upon the Contempt and incivility, with which the Dean has been treated; neither will you think any thing I have written too Light and Ludicrous, when you conſider that meer Indignation may provoke a man to Laugh. A Perſon that has been moſt eminently ſeviceable to the Church, is a Publick concern; and his Reputation ought not to be blaſted by every indiſcreet and paſſionate Writer. How Mr. <hi>Lowth</hi> will anſwer to his own Conſcience, this bold and repeated attempting to defame the Dean, at this time, upon falſe and frivolous pretences, I do not know. If he make an acknowledgement for the Injury, by a <hi>Recan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation as Publick as the Error, Scandal, and Offence,</hi> he will do like an <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt</hi> Man; but if he reſolve to write on ſtill, to exerciſe his Style, or to diſcharge a little more of his <hi>Choler,</hi> he may pleaſe himſelf: But unleſs he have ſomething more material to ſay than he has yet offer'd, all true Lovers of Learning, and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> will always continue upon the Dean's ſide.</p>
            <closer>I am, <salute>SIR</salute>
               <signed>Your Humble Servant.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>March</hi> the 10<hi>th.</hi> 1686/7.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:53010:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
